Juana Briones collection, circa 1960-2009 M1706
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Juana Briones Collection
circa 1960-2009
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
M1706
8 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Scope and Contents
Oral histories, memoirs, research files, photographs, newsclippings, maps, publications, adobe house preservation work, etc. Included is a 1870 census of Chinese workers, adobe samples from the house, information about the adobe structure, the historic structure report, the original house plan, the Juana Briones house tour docent handbook, "The Story of Donna Juana Briones de Miranda, " by Catherine Crary Elwood, 1962.
Biographical / Historical
Juana Briones (1802-1899) was a businesswoman and landowner in the San Francisco Bay Area.
General
These materials were collected by students in the Stanford History 201 course taught by Carol McKibben during the fall of 2009. The materials were given to Stanford University Libraries by various donors. At the time of this class, the historic adobe house was still standing but slated for demolition.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of various donors, transferred to Special Collections, 2009 and 2012. Accessions 2009-241 and 2012-124.
Santa Clara County (Calif.) -- History; California -- History -- 19th Century; Hispanic American women -- California -- Biography -- Sources; Briones, Juana, 1802-1899
- Series 1: Accession 2009-241
  - Publicity; website materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings from Juana House controversy (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs/maps/transparencies of propery/people (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Charles Palmer Nott (photographs, documents, art, slides) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Materials advocating preservation of Juana Briones house: correspondence, legal documents (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family research background: copies of newspapers, maps, emails, websites (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Current news" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Court Case summonings: emails, letters, case reports, legal documents (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Potential contacts: Briones house constituents, documents, emails, lists (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Plant/Herbal remedy books (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jeanne F. McDonnell correspondence (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - City Council correspondence (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Juana Briones Foundation contacts (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Briones House Foundation website materials (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Description of Photographs (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Marjorie Eaton material (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Documents of Authenticity of Briones House (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings re. demolition of Briones House, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous flyers (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Court Rulings, January 29, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - California Territorial Quarterly, Summer 2007: "We Care That She Cared: Dedication of a Headstone for Juana Briones," by Dr. Robert J. Chandler (pp. 34-43) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 4 audiocassettes: Hunt Interview tapes (2), Jeanne about Briones at Presidio (1), CA Women suffrage speech (1) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Briones photographs (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rally Information (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters from schoolchildren (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Preservation Memoir by Jeanne McDonnell (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Headstone Dedication (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - E-mail correspondence: Kent Lightfoot/Eugene McDonnell (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Juana Briones house plan, by Johanna Street (copy) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Juana Briones House Tour Docent Handbook (copy) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Juana Briones House Judgement, 2008 (copy) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Purchase of Juana Briones House (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous Board business (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - State Office of Historical Preservation (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "The Story of Donna Juana Briones de Miranda," by Catherine Crary Elwood, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - House Renovation/Preservation (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Nulman lawsuits (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Program and Educational Activities (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Financial Records: 9/99 - 12/31/2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Tax Information; Insurance papers (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer's Permanent File (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Financial records: Jan - Dec, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Financial records: 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financial records: 2000 - 5/2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Financial records: Jan - Dec, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Treasurer's Report: Jan - Dec, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CD's: Bolinas research (1); Land document (1) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - E-mails, Documents, etc. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - E-mails, Documents, etc. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Copies of 1830's documents (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Los Californianos (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings of web info re. land grants (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous documents (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Site of The Juana Briones House Historic Structure Report" (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Southern California Quarterly, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Juana Briones Foundation Living History Day (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Press Release (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Juana Briones Foundation brochure (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Handouts and Brochures (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Don Neilson material: maps, etc. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Women's History brochures (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Archaeology in the Bay Area (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Text for Briones House Foundation portfolio (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - African Roots (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Native American Information (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 1870 census: Chinese workers (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Mesa sale, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Other owners: Edith Cox Eaton (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Family documents (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Briones Foundation: Living History (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Latinas (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Folk Healing remedies (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Juana Briones Heritage Foundation materials (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Earthen Houses (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Mel Green - Mills Act Contract (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Historical Documents (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - California Register Application (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Barbara Judy Historic Structure Report (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - SHPO (State Office of Historical Preservation): papers to correct Dorothy Regnery error (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous articles, posts, etc. (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Land Swap (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Period History (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Olga Loya Performance (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Foundation: events (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - JBHF brochures (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Mills Act Agreement (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Location of Briones House: Table of Contents and "Exhibit A" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Authenticity of Earthen Walk: "Exhibit B" (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Land Ownership and Residency: "Exhibit C" (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Juana Briones Heritage Foundation Federal Tax Exemption application (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Juana Briones Heritage Foundation California State income tax exemption application (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Juana Briones Heritage Foundation records (part 1 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Juana Briones Heritage Foundation records (part 2 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Juana Briones Heritage Foundation records (part 3 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Briones Heritage Foundation agenda's, minutes, "quick bites" (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 8 CD's: photographs, powerpoint, etc. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Docent Handbook (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Akatiff material regarding Juana Briones Heritage Foundation (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - PAHA meeting, March 7, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - JBHF memos (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - JBHF Board material (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Juana Briones personal history (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - JBHF historical documents (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - JBHF: miscellaneous documents (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - JBHF: Docent training (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - JBHF: miscellaneous documents (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - JBHF: miscellaneous documents (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - "History vs. Hagiography," by Anthony Kirk, March 19, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - JBHF: miscellaneous documents (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Briones, Juana, 1802-1899
  - Property Permissions (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Marjorie Eaton/Lucretia Van Horn (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Briones property: photographs, letter excerpts (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - JBHF: miscellaneous documents (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - JBHF: miscellaneous documents (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Anthony Kirk's Refutations (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Dorothy Regnery research (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - National Trust Proposition (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Management (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Publicity (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - JBHF legal documents (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Tour agreement (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Fundraising (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Analysis: Green report (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Gil Sanchez: 1989 tour; 1996 letter (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Official documents: by-laws (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Bylaws (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Board (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Finance (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Barbara Judy Report (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Verification of 4155 Old Adobe Road as Original Briones House (Flat-box 6)
  - Adobe Rocks from original foundation (Card-box 7)
- Series 2: Accession 2012-124
  - McDonnell's Research and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Briones Murphy Lease (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Save Juana Briones House Sign (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nielson Draft (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - JBHF Web, Correspondence, Minutes (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Regnery & Response about House Authenticity (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Juana Briones House Misc. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Briones Programs, Activities & Events (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Preservation Effort, Correspondence, Newsletters, Magazines (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Earthquake and Preservation Agreement & WHM (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Juana Briones Photograph (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mayfield Maps / Mesa Family (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Digital Research (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Briones Related Maps (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nulman Court Documents and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - San Francisco Writings and Maps (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Historic Palque, Support Letters, Application (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Garcia Family (Family Tree) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Archtecture Material, Encajonado (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Historic Structure Report (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Childrens' Letters to Briones (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - New Clippings Honoring Briones (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Briones House Tours/ Docent Training (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Preservation, Demolition) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - WHM Historic Building Inventory (1987) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Women's Heritage Museum Newsletters & Archives (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fava Research (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Land Transaction & Petitions for Land (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Spanish Documents and Translations, Letters from Juana (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Juana Briones Testimonies (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Family & Geneology Decendants (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Census (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ojo de Agua Court Case, Maps, Land Grant Documents (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Preservation Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - News Clippings (1950s-1980s) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Briones Related Writings (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - House Photographs Labeled (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Presidio Maps, Drawings & Writings (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gravesite (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Nott Family (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Eaton Documents (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Journal of the West (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Thomas Dimas Mesa (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Digital Preservation DVDs and Woolley email CD (Half-box 2, Folder 1)
  - San Francisco Chronicle article: November 30, 2010 (Half-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Briones House photographs, maps, sketches (Half-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous slides (Half-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Briones House events: photographs (Half-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Briones House photographs, maps, sketches (Half-box 2, Folder 6)